<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" id="City of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2024-8" codify:doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" >
  <num>2024-8</num>
  <heading type="short">Youth Commissioners</heading>
  <heading type="long">Amending San Mateo Municipal Code Chapters 2.15, 2.28, and 2.29 to amend the organization of the Library Board, Sustainability and Infrastructure Commission, and Senior Citizens Commission to include two non-voting youth advisory members (youth commissioners)</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-10-03</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="ord" url="./adopted/2024-8.pdf">Ord. No. 2024-8</citation>
      <citation type="bb">City of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2024-8</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <introduced>2024-08-19</introduced>
      <adopted>2024-09-03</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the San Mateo Municipal Code establishes that the Library Board (<cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.15">Chapter 2.15</cite>), Sustainability and Infrastructure Commission (<cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.28">Chapter 2.28</cite>), and Senior Citizens Commission (<cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.29">Chapter 2.29</cite>) shall each have five members appointed by the City Council; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the City Council Strategic Plan for fiscal year 2023-24 included exploring the increasing of representation of youth and seniors on City Boards and Commissions; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on March 4, 2024, the City Council directed staff to provide for the appointment of youth members to the Library Board, Senior Citizens Commission, and Sustainability and Infrastructure Commission.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE,</conjunction>
      <text>THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SAN MATEO ORDAINS AS FOLLOWS:</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <text><cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.15.010">Section 2.15.010 of the San Mateo Municipal Code</cite> is amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <section>
        <codify:replace path="|2.15.010"/>
        <num>2.15.010</num>
        <heading>ORGANIZATION—POWERS—DUTIES.</heading>
        <text>The public library shall be governed by a library board of trustees. There is and shall be a library board of trustees consisting of five members appointed by the City Council with the powers and duties as set forth in <cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Charter" path="6.01">Section 6.01 of the Charter of the City</cite> and as provided for in <cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.15">this chapter</cite>. In addition, the library board shall include two non-voting youth advisory members who must be at least 13 years old, and no more than 17 years old at the time of appointment ("Youth Board Members"). Youth Board Members must present written documentation of parental or guardian consent to be considered for appointment. Youth Board Members shall serve only in an advisory capacity and shall not count towards a quorum of the commission.</text>
        <text>Each member shall serve at the pleasure of the Council and for a term of four years, or until the appointment and qualification of a successor. Each Youth Board Member shall serve at the pleasure of the Council for a term of one year and until the appointment and qualification of a successor. Youth Board Members may be reappointed for one additional one-year term.</text>
      </section>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <text><cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.28.010">Section 2.28.010 of the San Mateo Municipal Code</cite> is amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <section>
        <codify:replace path="|2.28.010"/>
        <num>2.28.010</num>
        <heading>ORGANIZATION.</heading>
        <text>The commission shall have five members appointed by the Council.  In addition, the commission shall have two non-voting youth advisory members who must be at least 13 years old, and no more than 17 years old at the time of appointment ("Youth Commissioners"). Youth Commissioners must also present written documentation of parental or guardian consent to be considered for appointment. Youth Commissioners shall serve only in an advisory capacity and shall not count towards a quorum of the commission.</text>
        <text>The members of the commission shall be appointed for four-year terms or until the appointment of a successor, except that the initial terms of the first members appointed shall be determined by lot at their first meeting so that each year one or more terms will expire. Each Youth Commissioner shall serve at the pleasure of the Council for a term of one year and until the appointment and qualification of a successor. Youth Commissioners may be reappointed for one additional one-year term.</text>
      </section>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>3</num>
    <text><cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Code" path="2.29.010">Section 2.29.010 of the San Mateo Municipal Code</cite> is amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <section>
        <codify:replace path="|2.29.010"/>
        <num>2.29.010</num>
        <heading>ORGANIZATION.</heading>
        <text>The senior citizens commission of the City shall consist of no more than five members appointed by the Council. The President of the Senior Advisory Council, or designee, shall be an ex-officio member of the Senior Citizens Commission without the right to vote. Members shall be persons who display an interest in and appreciation of senior affairs. In addition, the commission shall have two non-voting youth advisory members who must be at least 13 years old, and no more than 17 years old at the time of appointment ("Youth Commissioners"). Youth Commissioners must present written documentation of parental or guardian consent to be considered for appointment. Youth Commissioners shall serve only in an advisory capacity and shall not count towards a quorum of the commission.</text>
        <text>Each member of the senior citizens commission shall serve at the pleasure of the Council and for a term of four years or until the appointment of a successor, except that the initial terms of the first members appointed shall be determined by lot at their first meeting so that each year at least one term will expire. Thereafter, all appointments shall be for a term of four years. Each Youth Commissioner shall serve at the pleasure of the Council for a term of one year and until the appointment and qualification of a successor. Youth Commissioners may be reappointed for one additional one-year term.</text>
      </section>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>4</num>
    <heading>Environmental Determination.</heading>
    <text>In accordance with California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA) Guidelines, Section 15378(b)(5)., this action is not a project subject to CEQA, because it is an organizational or administrative activity that will not result in direct or indirect physical changes in the environment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>5</num>
    <heading>Severability.</heading>
    <text>In the event any section, clause or provision of this ordinance shall be determined invalid or unconstitutional, such section, clause or provision shall be deemed severable and all other sections or portions hereof shall remain in full force and effect.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>6</num>
    <heading>Publication.</heading>
    <text>This ordinance shall be published in summary in a newspaper of general circulation, posted in the City Clerk's Office, and posted on the City's website, all in accord with <cite doc="City of San Mateo, Cal., Charter" path="2.15">Section 2.15 of the City Charter</cite>.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>7</num>
    <heading>Legislative History and Effective Date.</heading>
    <text>This ordinance was introduced on August 19, 2024, and adopted on September 3, 2024, and shall be effective 30 days after its adoption.</text>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>The foregoing ordinance was adopted by the City Council of the City of San Mateo, State of California by the following vote:</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>AYES</th>
          <td>Council Members Diaz Nash, Newsom, Loraine, Hedges, and Lee</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>NOES</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
          <td>None</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>ATTEST:</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
